A Guide to the Amelia County (Va.) Deeds, 1734-1914
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Amelia County (Va.) Deeds, 1734-1914
The Library of Virginia
44.2 cubic feet (97 boxes); 13 volumes
Amelia County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Amelia County (Va.) Bills of Sale and Deeds,1734-1864, involving enslaved and free Black and multiracial individuals are digitized and available through Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative Digital Collection on the Library of Virginia website. Please use digital images.
For Amelia County (Va.) Deed Books, 1734-1765, use microfilm Amelia County (Va.) Reels 1-4
Acquisition Information
Loose Deeds, 1734-1914, came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Amelia County in 2004 under accession 41505.
Deed Book 1 and bonds ,1734-1741, came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Amelia County in 1966 under accession 26511.
Index to Deeds, 1904-1914, came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Amelia County in under accession 34741.
Remaining material came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Amelia County in an undated accession.
Alternative Form Available
Deed Books microfilm Amelia County (Va.) Reels 1-4.
Historical Information
Context for Record Type: Bills of sale are written agreements which convey title of property, including enslaved people, from seller to buyer. Under the system of chattel slavery, laws permitted enslavers to treat enslaved people as personal possessions in the same manner as livestock, farm equipment, or household items. Enslaved people could be bought or sold without regard to their personal relationships or free will. Bills of sale record the name of the seller, the names of enslaved people being sold and their price, and the name of the buyer. Given that they involved a property transaction, bills of sale were commonly recorded and filed with deeds in the local court. However, there was no official requirement that the transfer of an enslaved person be recorded unless necessary for legal purposes such as a court case or an estate settlement. Enslaved people could also be transferred through a deed of gift, there was no money transaction involved in this case, which distinguishes this record from a bill of sale. Enslavers and their family members often transferred enslaved people between themselves in this manner.
Deeds are written agreements which convey title of property, such as an enslaved person, from one individual to another. These include the voluntary transfer of enslaved people between family members with no financial transaction involved. Deeds include the names of the grantors, grantees, and enslaved people. Clerks proved, acknowledged, and recorded deeds in the local court.
Locality History: Amelia County was named for Amelia Sophia Eleanora, daughter of King George II. It was formed from Prince George and Brunswick Counties by an act passed in 1734 to take effect on 25 March 1735. The county court first met on 9 May 1735.
Scope and Content
Amelia County (Va.) Deeds, 1734-1914, consist of deeds of bargain and sale, deeds of gift, mortgages, bills of sale, and deeds of trust. Included are eight boxes of processed and indexed material consisting of bills of sale and deeds,1743-1864, involving free and enslaved Black individuals.
Deeds of bargain and sale are the most recorded deed in which one individual sells property, usually land, but occasionally personal property, to another individual. Such deeds show the names of the grantor and grantee, the residence of both parties, a description of what is being sold, the consideration (or price), the location of the tract of land, the tract's boundaries, and any limitations on the property being sold. The deed was signed by the grantor, and possibly his wife or anyone else having a claim to the property, and by at least two witnesses. Appended to the deed may be a memorandum of livery of seisin, stating that the property has changed hands and that peaceful possession has taken place.
Deeds of gift are often found transferring property, either real or personal including enslaved people, from one individual to another "for love and affection." The degree of kinship, if any, between the grantor and grantee is sometimes stated. Information recorded included name(s) of the grantor(s), grantee(s), and enslaved people. Deeds of gift were proved and recorded in the local court.
Mortgages and deeds of trust were deeds where one party is indebted to another and transfers or mortgages property to a third party to secure the debt.
Bills of sale are written agreements which convey title of property, such as an enslaved person, from seller to buyer. Bills of sale record the name of the seller, the names of enslaved persons being sold and their price, and the name of the buyer. Given that they involved a property transaction, bills of sale were commonly recorded and filed with deeds in the local court.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged
Series I: Deeds and bills of sale,1734-1864, involving free and enslaved people, arranged chronologically
Series II: Deeds and records related to, 1734-1914, arranged chronologically
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
See also: Amelia County (Va.) Deeds of Emancipation, 1767-1859
Records related to free and enslaved people of Amelia County (Va.) and other localities are available through the Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative Digital Collection on the Library of Virginia website.
Additional Amelia County (Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia.Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."
Contents List
- Deeds and Bills of Sale, relating to free and enslaved Black and multiracial persons, 1743-1864, 3.6 cubic feet (8 boxes)
  arranged chronologically
  - Deeds 1743-1784 Free and Enslaved People
  - Deeds 1785-1806 Free and Enslaved People
  - Deeds 1807-1823 Free and Enslaved People
  - Deeds 1824-1829 Free and Enslaved People
  - Deeds 1830-1839 Free and Enslaved People
  - Deeds 1840-1848 Free and Enslaved People
  - Deeds 1849-1864 Free and Enslaved People
  - Unrecorded and Partially Proven Deeds 1766-1856 Free and Enslaved People
- Deeds and records relating to, 1734-1914, 40.6 cubic feet (89 boxes); 13 volumes
  - Deeds, 1734-1913
    - Deeds 1734-1791 A-BE
    - Deeds 1734-1791 BEV-BRY
    - Deeds 1734-1791 BU-CLE
    - Deeds 1734-1791 CO-CRY
    - Deeds 1734-1791 DAL-EL
    - Deeds 1734-1791 ELM-FORD
    - Deeds 1734-1791 FORE-GORE
    - Deeds 1734-1791 GRE-HAS
    - Deeds 1734-1791 HAT-HUD
    - Deeds 1734-1791 HUG-JES
    - Deeds 1734-1791 JET-JON
    - Deeds 1734-1791 JONES-LIG
    - Deeds 1734-1791 LIGO-MAY
    - Deeds 1734-1791 MEA-MOU
    - Deeds 1734-1791 MU-OV
    - Deeds 1734-1791 PAC-Q
    - Deeds 1734-1791 RAD-SHO
    - Deeds 1734-1791 SI-TAL
    - Deeds 1734-1791 TAN-TU
    - Deeds 1734-1791 VAD-WAL
    - Deeds 1734-1791 WAR-WH
    - Deeds 1734-1791 WIL-WING
    - Deeds 1734-1791 WINN-Z
    - Deeds 1792-1809 AD-BOOK
    - Deeds 1792-1809 BOOT-COLE
    - Deeds 1792-1810
    - Deeds 1792-1809
    - Deeds 1810-1812
    - Deeds 1812-1814
    - Deeds 1814-1816
    - Deeds 1816-1818
    - Deeds 1818-1819
    - Deeds 1820-1821
    - Deeds 1822-1823
    - Deeds 1824-1825
    - Deeds 1825-1826
    - Deeds 1826-1827
    - Deeds 1828-1829 A-J
    - Deeds 1829-1831 L-H
    - Deeds 1831-1832 J-W
    - Deeds 1833 A-W
    - Deeds 1834-1835 A-W
    - Deeds 1836-1837
    - Deeds 1838-1839
    - Deeds 1840-1841
    - Deeds 1842-1843 J
    - Deeds 1843-1845 K
    - Deeds 1846-1848
    - Deeds 1849-1851
    - Deeds 1852-1854
    - Deeds 1855-1856
    - Deeds 1857-1858
    - Deeds 1859-1861
    - Deeds 1862-1866
    - Deeds 1867-1870 E
    - Deeds 1870-1871 F-J
    - Deeds 1871-1873
    - Deeds 1874-1876 A-C
    - Deeds 1876-1878 D-J
    - Deeds 1878-1880 M-G
    - Deeds 1880-1881 H
    - Deeds 1882-1883 F
    - Deeds 1883-1885 G-L
    - Deeds 1885-1886 M-Y
    - Deeds 1887-1888 A-J
    - Deeds 1888-1889 M
    - Deeds 1890
    - Deeds 1891-1893 A
    - Deeds 1894-1895 A-W
    - Deeds 1896-1897 B-W
    - Deeds 1898-1899 W
    - Deeds 1900-1901 A-W
    - Deeds 1902-1903 B-W
    - Deeds 1904
    - Deeds 1905
    - Deeds 1906 A-MI
    - Deeds 1906 MO-W
    - Deeds 1907 A-S
    - Deeds 1907-1908 T-R
    - Deeds 1908-1909 S-G
    - Deeds 1909 H-W
    - Deeds 1910 A-S
    - Deeds 1910-1911 T-O
    - Deeds 1911-1912 P-B
    - Deeds 1912 C-P
    - Deeds 1912-1913 R-B
    - Deeds 1913 C-N
    - Deeds 1913 O-Y
    - Articles of Agreement/Memorandum of Agreements/Contracts; Boundary Line Establishment; Certificates of Satisfaction; Deeds of Gift; Deeds of Trust; Ejectments; Land Inquisitions; Mill Petitions; Miscellaneous Land Records; Processioners' Returns 1739-1907, undated
  - Deed Books and Indexes, 1734-1914
    - Deed Book #1 and Bonds 1734-1743;1735-1741
    - Deed Book #6 1756-1759
    - Deed Book (copy) 1742-1747
    - Deed Book [copy] 1750-1754
    - Deed Book [copy] 1759-1762 (Part 2)
    - Deed Book [copy] 1759-1762 (Part 1)
    - Deed Book [copy] 1768-1769
    - Deed Book [copy] 1773-1774
    - Index [to Deed Book No. 5] 1749-1757
    - Index to Deeds (Acc. 34741, No. 41) 1904-1907
    - Index to Deeds (Acc. 34741, No. 42) 1907-1911
    - Index to Deeds (Acc. 34741, No. 43) 1911-1914
    - Records on Appeal; Deeds 1810-1823